A Guide to the Murat W. Williams & Williams Family Papers 1884-1991
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Murat W. Williams & Williams Family Papers 1884-1991
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10724-b
ca. 6,500 items (29 Hollinger boxes, ca.12 linear shelf feet)
This collection consists of the additional papers of Ambassador Murat W. Williams and the Williams Family, ca 1884-1991, primarily the business, legal, and professional papers, correspondence, and diaries, of Ambassador Murat W. Williams and Joan Cunningham Williams. The papers also contain correspondence, bound volumes, photographs and miscellaneous material of other Williams family members, including Dr. Ennion G. Williams, Lewis Catlett Williams, John Langbourne Williams and John Skelton Williams.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Michael C. Williams, Chevy Chase, Maryland, and his siblings, Kathleen M. Williams, Brigid C. Williams, and Nicholas M. Williams on June 10, 1998.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the additional papers of Ambassador Murat W. Williams and the Williams family, ca. 1884-1991, and n.d., primarily the business, legal, and professional papers, correspondence, and diaries, of Ambassador Murat W. Williams and Joan Cunningham Williams.
The papers also contain correspondence, bound volumes, photographs and miscellaneous material of other Williams family members, including Dr. Ennion G. Williams, Lewis Catlett Williams, John Langbourne Williams and John Skelton Williams. For more information about the Williams family and Murat Williams, please consult the guide for Accession #10724.
The majority of the correspondence (Series I) is with Murat Williams, who also kept several separate folders of correspondence with individuals, including Dr. Fabio Castillo, Douglas Southall Freeman, Walter La Feber, John B. Oakes, Josefina Tudelo, Robert E. Wilson, and Frank G. Wisner. Most of the financial records (Series II) concern the Cunningham family estates and trusts, especially those of his wife, Joan Cunningham Williams, and the investments of Murat and Joan Williams.
Because of the quantity of material in the collection concerning El Salvador, it has been placed in a separate series (Series III), which includes articles, speeches, printed material, news clippings, and correspondence about El Salvador, as well as several miscellaneous folders. Murat Williams served as the Ambassador to El Salvador from 1961-1964, and was appointed by President John F. Kennedy.
The fourth series consists of topical and miscellaneous papers including: files on the political campaigns of Armistead Boothe, Eugene McCarthy, and Murat Williams; biographical information about Murat Williams; church auxiliary papers and Christmas stories written by Murat's mother, Maria Ward Skelton Williams; many news clippings concerning politics in Virginia and some about the career of Murat Williams; news clippings and a topical file on John Skelton Williams; the Nora Isabella Samuelli case; the White Burkett Miller Center of Public Affairs and Ken Thompson; and a file on Frederick Palmer Webber. Files pertaining directly to Murat Williams include: various articles & writings by Murat Williams, an oral history interview transcript for the John Kennedy Library, personnel records while in service with the State Department, and speeches by Williams.
Series five chiefly contains bound volumes, which have been divided into two subseries. Williams family members represented in the first subseries are John L. Williams (1831-1915), Mrs. Maria Ward Skelton Williams, and M.W. Williams. The second subseries has volumes pertaining only to Murat Williams, including calendars, desk diaries, and pocket diaries, from 1950-1988. Other items in this series include oversize certificates for Murat Williams' navy and foreign service, reel-to-reel recordings and a film reel, 1970-1972, concerning Williams' political campaigns.
Organization
Series I: Correspondence (Boxes 1-5)
Series II: Financial Papers (Boxes 6-9)
Series III: El Salvador & Central America (Boxes 10-12)
Series IV: Topical & Miscellaneous Papers (Boxes 13- 16)
Series V: Bound Volumes (Boxes 17-29), Oversize Material (OVERSIZE BOX P-24) & Audiotape Recordings
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence of Dr. Fabio Castillo with Murat Williams 1969-1990, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Douglas Southall Freeman with Murat Williams 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Walter La Feber with Murat Williams 1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of John B. Oakes with Murat Williams 1983-1985, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re Promotion of Murat W. Williams to Career Minister 1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Dr. Ennion G. Williams 1899, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Joan Cunningham [Williams] 1938-1945, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Murat Williams to Josefina Tudelo 1940-1942, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Murat Williams 1935-1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Murat Williams 1950-1961, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of Murat Williams 1962-1966, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of Murat Williams 1967-1984 Aug, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Murat Williams 1984 Sep-1991, n.d., 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence of Robert E. Wilson with Murat Williams 1981-1985 (Box 5)
  - Post cards & Greeting cards 1935-1984 (Box 5)
- Financial Papers
  - Aurora Equity Fund, Inc. 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Automobile 1953-1957, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Automobile Insurance 1963-1965 (Box 6)
  - Bank of New York 1981-1983 (Box 6)
  - Bessemer Trust Company, N.A. 1977-1980 (Box 6)
  - Brokaw, Schaenen, Clancy & Co. - Correspondence 1965-1971 (Box 6)
  - Brokaw, Schaenen, Clancy & Co. - Statements of Account 1965-1969 (Box 6)
  - Central National Bank of Richmond, Virginia - Correspondence 1963-1976 (Box 6)
  - Central National Bank of Richmond, Virginia - Statements of Account 1963-1970 (Box 6)
  - Central Trust Company, Rochester, New York 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - Check Books of Joan Cunningham Williams 1972-1988 (Box 6)
  - Christy & Viener - Correspondence with the Williams 1977 (Box 6)
  - Clark County, Virginia, Property Purchase 1958, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Crossbar Realty, Inc. 1960-1967, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Estate of Francis E. Cunningham - Correspondence and Legal Documents ca. 1941-1961 (Box 6)
  - Estate of Francis E. Cunningham - Correspondence and Legal Documents ca. 1965-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Estate of Kathleen M. Cunningham 1968-1974, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Fertica 1968 (Box 7)
  - Financial Consulting 1964-1974, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Financial Planning and Investment 1961-1984, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Howe and Rusling, Inc. 1963-1966 (Box 7)
  - James Cunningham, Son & Co., Inc. 1960-1967, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Koster, Sheppard & Co. - Correspondence 1964-1967 (Box 7)
  - Lincoln First Bank of Rochester - Correspondence 1971-1974 (Box 7)
  - Lincoln first Bank of Rochester - Statements for Kathleen Cunningham Estate 1971-1974, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Lincoln First Bank of Rochester, New York - Tax Returns for Cunningham Trust Account 1974, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Lincoln Rochester Trust Company - Correspondence with Joan C. Williams 1959-1972 (Box 8)
  - Lincoln Rochester Trust Company - Statements and Investments Review for Joan C. Williams 1959-1972, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Merrill Lynch, Pierce, Fenner, & Smith, Inc., Rochester, New York 1963-1965 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Financial 1948-1980 (Box 8)
  - National Bank & Trust Company, Charlottesville, Virginia 1972 (Box 8)
  - Personal & Miscellaneous Paid Bills 1954-1956, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Real Estate Papers & Correspondence of Murat & Joan Williams 1954-1956 (Box 8)
  - Rochester Museum and Science Center 1971-1973, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Security & Storage Bills & Documents for Murat & Joan Williams 1954-1973 (Box 9)
  - Security Trust Company, Rochester, New York 1963-1964 (Box 9)
  - State-Planters Bank of Commerce and Trusts, Richmond, Virginia 1945-1963 (Box 9)
  - United States Trust Company - Correspondence with the Williams 1972-1977, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - United States Trust Company - Statements of Joan C. Williams 1970-1977, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - United Virginia Bank - Lists of Assets of the Williams 1971-1977 (Box 9)
- El Salvador & Central America
  - Articles re El Salvador 1963-1990, n.d., 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Articles and some letters re El Salvador from Charles Clements 1983-1986, n.d., 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Asylum From El Salvador 1981-1984, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Caribbean Basin Information Project 1963-1985, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Central America Papers Project 1984-1985, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Chiefs of Station - El Salvador 1984, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Commission on the United States - Central American Relations 1982-1987 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence re El Salvador 1950-1969 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence re El Salvador 1980-1989, n.d., 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Death Squads 1961-1984, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Departure Messages - San Salvador 1964 (Box 11)
  - Films re El Salvador 1981-1985, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Madison Mills Conference & Gabriel Siri 1971 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous re El Salvador 1947-1990 (Box 11)
  - News clippings re El Salvador 1960-1990, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - News clippings re El Salvador n.d. (Box 12)
  - Photographs re El Salvador 1961, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Printed Material re El Salvador 1980-1990, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Speeches re El Salvador by Murat Williams 1961-1990, n.d., 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Witness to War: An American doctor in El Salvador by Charles Clements, M.D. 1984, Typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 12)
- Topical & Miscellaneous papers
  - American Association of University Women 1985-1986 (Box 13)
  - Articles 1952-1990, n.d., 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Artwork by the Williams children n.d. (Box 13)
  - Association of College Editors 1934 (Box 13)
  - Biographical Sketches & Notices of Murat Williams, including GPO document re his nomination as Ambassador to El Salvador ca. 1961-1987 (Box 13)
  - Campaign of Armistead Boothe, including correspondence 1965-1966, n.d., 3 folders (Box 13)
  - "Campaign of Eugene McCarthy in Virginia" by Murat Williams 1968 (Box 13)
  - Campaign of Murat Williams against J. Kenneth Robinson in the Congressional 7th District 1970, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Christmas Stories by Mrs. Lewis C. Williams ca. 1951-1958 (Box 14)
  - Church Auxiliary Papers of [Mrs. Lewis C. Williams?] n.d. (Box 14)
  - Conservation & Edgewood Farm 1980-1985, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Dictionary of Foreign Affairs Terms & Cliches kept by Murat Williams n.d. (Box 14)
  - "Edgewood," Madison County, Virginia 1941-1966 (Box 14)
  - Guest Lists While in Israel 1959-1960 (Box 14)
  - Medical File 1986-1990, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1944-1986, n.d. (Box 14)
  - News clippings 1935-1989 (Box 14)
  - News clippings re Politics 1965-1974, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - News clippings re John Skelton Williams, Comptroller of the Currency 1913 (Box 14)
  - Oral History Interview with Murat W. Williams for the John F. Kennedy Library 1970 Jun 22, transcript (Box 14)
  - Personnel Records of Murat Williams 1946-1958 (Box 14)
  - Personnel Records of Murat Williams 1959-1965 (Box 15)
  - Photographs, including those of the 1970 Campaign 1916, ca. 1963-1985, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Public Welfare Foundation 1988-1991 (Box 15)
  - Rhodes Scholars Reunion 1981-1984 (Box 15)
  - Nora Isabella Samuelli Case 1963 (Box 15)
  - Speeches by Murat Williams 1946-1986, n.d., 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Speeches by Murat Williams n.d. (Box 16)
  - Travel 1961-1985 (Box 16)
  - University of Chicago Visit 1983-1984 (Box 16)
  - University of Virginia Summer on the Lawn 1984 (Box 16)
  - Virginia Historical Society Talk "My How Things Have Changed!" by Mary Tyler Freeman Cheek 1990 Nov 7 (Box 16)
  - George Washington 1990 (Box 16)
  - Frederick Palmer Webber (1914-1986) 1978-1987, n.d. (Box 16)
  - White Burkett Miller Center of Public Affairs 1988-1991, n.d. (Box 16)
  - John Skelton Williams 1895-1983, n.d. (Box 16)
  - Williams Family 1884, 1926-1981, n.d. (Box 16)
  - Writings & Outlines of Murat Williams n.d. (Box 16)
- Bound Volumes, Oversize Material & Audiotape Recordings
  - Williams Family
    - Account Book 1867-1881, Bound volume (Box 17)
    - Address Books n.d., 3 bound volumes (Box 17)
    - Christmas Card & Presents Record 1951, Bound volume (Box 17)
    - Diaries of John L. Williams 1910, 1912, 1914, 3 bound volumes (Box 17)
    - Diary of Book Titles kept by John L Williams n.d., Bound volume (Box 17)
    - Diaries of [Mrs. Lewis C. Williams] 1937-1941, 1947, 1953, 7 bound volumes (Box 17)
    - Garden Book 1910-1911, Bound volume (Box 18)
    - Government Contol of Industry in Great Britain As Demonstrated In Iron and Steel by M.W. Williams at Oxford 1939, Bound volume (Box 18)
    - Guest Books 1894-1895, 1906, n.d., 3 bound volumes (Box 18)
    - Housebold Linen Book 1926-1927, Bound volume (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous n.d., 2 bound volumes (Box 18)
    - St. Thomas Church Business Women's Circle Report on a general convention in Cincinnati 1937, Bound volume (Box 18)
    - Wedding Gift Record Books for Maria Ward & Lewis C. Williams 1901-1902, Bound volume (Box 18)
  - Murat Williams
    - Calendars of Murat Williams 1950-1977, 5 bound volumes (Box 19)
    - Calendars of Murat Williams 1978-1986, 2 bound volumes (Box 20)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1955-1956, 1959, 3 bound volumes (Box 20)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1960-1963, 4 bound volumes (Box 21)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1964-1967, 4 bound volumes (Box 22)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1968-1971, 4 bound volumes (Box 23)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1972-1974, 3 bound volumes (Box 24)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1976-1978, 3 bound volumes (Box 25)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1979-1981, 3 bound volumes (Box 26)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1982-1984, 3 bound volumes (Box 27)
    - Desk Diaries of Murat Williams 1985-1987, 3 bound volumes (Box 28)
    - Desk Diary of Murat Williams 1988, Bound volume (Box 29)
    - Pocket Diaries of Murat Williams 1957, 1959, 1963, 3 bound volumes (Box 29)
    - Pocket Diaries of Murat Williams 1969-1987, 18 bound volumes (Box 29)
    - Honorable Discharge Certificate from the United State Navy Reserves for Murat Williams 1956 May 15 (Oversize P-24)
    - Foreign Service Appointment Certificates of Murat Williams 1947, 1951, 1954, 1958 (Oversize P-24)
    - 3 reel-to-reel recordings for the political campaign of Murat Williams ca. 1970-1972
    - reel-to-reel recording of Buena Vista Speech by Murat Williams 1970 Oct 26
    - WDBJ-TV film of the [Democratic Convention?] re the political campaign of Murat Williams
    - reel-to-reel recording for the political campaign of Murat Williams